What's immediate and ephemeral seems to dominate our lives, our economy and our politics. It's so easy to get caught up in the number of steps we took today or the latest tweet from a high-profile figure. It's easy for businesses to get caught up in making immediate profits and neglect what's good for future invention. And it's far too easy for governments to stand by while fisheries and farmland are depleted instead of conserved to feed future generations. I have a feeling that, at this rate, it's going to be hard for our generation to be remembered as good ancestors. If you think about it, our species evolved to think ahead, to chart the stars, dream of the afterlife, sow seeds for later harvest. Some scientists call this superpower that we have "mental time travel," and it's responsible for pretty much everything we call human civilization, from farming to the Magna Carta to the internet -- all first conjured in the minds of humans. But let's get real: if we look around us today, we don't exactly seem to be using this superpower quite enough, and that begs the question: Why not? What's wrong is how our communities, businesses and institutions are designed. They're designed in a way that's impairing our foresight. I want to talk to you about the three key mistakes that I think we're making. The first mistake is what we measure. When we look at the quarterly profits of a company or its near-term stock price, that's often not a great measure of whether that company is going to grow its market share or be inventive in the long run. When we glue ourselves to the test scores that kids bring back from school, that's not necessarily what's great for those kids' learning and curiosity in the long run. We're not measuring what really matters in the future. The second mistake we're making that impairs our foresight is what we reward. When we celebrate a political leader or a business leader for the disaster she just cleaned up or the announcement she just made, we're not motivating that leader to invest in preventing those disasters in the first place, or to put down payments on the future by protecting communities from floods or fighting inequality or investing in research and education. The third mistake that impairs our foresight is what we fail to imagine. Now, when we do think about the future, we tend to focus on predicting exactly what's next, whether we're using horoscopes or algorithms to do that. But we spend a lot less time imagining all the possibilities the future holds. When the Ebola outbreak emerged in 2014 in West Africa, public health officials around the world had early warning signs and predictive tools that showed how that outbreak might spread, but they failed to fathom that it would, and they failed to act in time to intervene, and the epidemic grew to kill more than 11,000 people. When people with lots of resources and good forecasts don't prepare for deadly hurricanes, they're often failing to imagine how dangerous they can be. Now, none of these mistakes that I've described, as dismal as they might sound, are inevitable. In fact, they're all avoidable. What we need to make better decisions about the future are tools that can aid our foresight, tools that can help us think ahead. Think of these as something like the telescopes that ship captains of yore used when they scanned the horizon. Only instead of for looking across distance and the ocean, these tools are for looking across time to the future. I want to share with you a few of the tools that I've found in my research that I think can help us with foresight. The first tool I want to share with you I think of as making the long game pay now. This is Wes Jackson, a farmer I spent some time with in Kansas. And Jackson knows that the way that most crops are grown around the world today is stripping the earth of the fertile topsoil we need to feed future generations. He got together with a group of scientists, and they bred perennial grain crops which have deep roots that anchor the fertile topsoil of a farm, preventing erosion and protecting future harvests. But they also knew that in order to get farmers to grow these crops in the short run, they needed to boost the annual yields of the crops and find companies willing to make cereal and beer using the grains so that farmers could reap profits today by doing what's good for tomorrow. And this is a tried-and-true strategy. In fact, it was used by George Washington Carver in the South of the United States after the Civil War in the early 20th century. A lot of people have probably heard of Carver's 300 uses for the peanut, the products and recipes that he came up with that made the peanut so popular. But not everyone knows why Carver did that. He was trying to help poor Alabama sharecroppers whose cotton yields were declining, and he knew that planting peanuts in their fields would replenish those soils so that their cotton yields would be better a few years later. But he also knew it needed to be lucrative for them in the short run. Alright, so let's talk about another tool for foresight. This one I like to think of as keeping the memory of the past alive to help us imagine the future. So I went to Fukushima, Japan on the sixth anniversary of the nuclear reactor disaster there that followed the Tohoku earthquake and tsunami of 2011. When I was there, I learned about the Onagawa Nuclear Power Station, which was even closer to the epicenter of that earthquake than the infamous Fukushima Daiichi that we all know about. In Onagawa, people in the city actually fled to the nuclear power plant as a place of refuge. It was that safe. It was spared by the tsunamis. It was the foresight of just one engineer, Yanosuke Hirai, that made that happen. In the 1960s, he fought to build that power plant farther back from the coast at higher elevation and with a higher sea wall. He knew the story of his hometown shrine, which had flooded in the year 869 after a tsunami. It was his knowledge of history that allowed him to imagine what others could not. OK, one more tool of foresight. This one I think of as creating shared heirlooms. These are lobster fishermen on the Pacific coast of Mexico, and they're the ones who taught me this. They have protected their lobster harvest there for nearly a century, and they've done that by treating it as a shared resource that they're passing on to their collected children and grandchildren. They carefully measure what they catch so that they're not taking the breeding lobster out of the ocean. Across North America, there are more than 30 fisheries that are doing something vaguely similar to this. They're creating long-term stakes in the fisheries known as catch shares which get fishermen to be motivated not just in taking whatever they can from the ocean today but in its long-term survival. Now there are many, many more tools of foresight I would love to share with you, and they come from all kinds of places: investment firms that look beyond near-term stock prices, states that have freed their elections from the immediate interests of campaign financiers. And we're going to need to marshal as many of these tools as we can if we want to rethink what we measure, change what we reward and be brave enough to imagine what lies ahead. Not all this is going to be easy, as you can imagine. Some of these tools we can pick up in our own lives, some we're going to need to do in businesses or in communities, and some we need to do as a society. The future is worth this effort. My own inspiration to keep up this effort is the instrument I shared with you. It's called a dilruba, and it was custom-made for my great-grandfather. He was a well-known music and art critic in India in the early 20th century. My great-grandfather had the foresight to protect this instrument at a time when my great-grandmother was pawning off all their belongings, but that's another story. He protected it by giving it to the next generation, by giving it to my grandmother, and she gave it to me. When I first heard the sound of this instrument, it haunted me. It felt like hearing a wanderer in the Himalayan fog. It felt like hearing a voice from the past. (Music) (Music ends) That's my friend Simran Singh playing the dilruba. When I play it, it sounds like a cat's dying somewhere, so you're welcome. (Laughter) This instrument is in my home today, but it doesn't actually belong to me. It's my role to shepherd it in time, and that feels more meaningful to me than just owning it for today. This instrument positions me as both a descendant and an ancestor. It makes me feel part of a story bigger than my own. And this, I believe, is the single most powerful way we can reclaim foresight: by seeing ourselves as the good ancestors we long to be, ancestors not just to our own children but to all humanity. Whatever your heirloom is, however big or small, protect it and know that its music can resonate for generations. Thank you. (Applause)
Lo inmediato, lo efímero parece dominar nuestras vidas, nuestra economía y nuestra política. Es tan fácil enfrascarnos en la cantidad de pasos que dimos hoy o en el último tweet de alguna figura prominente. Para las empresas, es fácil dejarse llevar por el beneficio inmediato y dejar de lado cosas que son buenas para el futuro. Y a los Gobiernos les resulta muy fácil quedarse de brazos cruzados mientras se agotan los recursos marítimos y agropecuarios, en lugar de preservarlos para alimentar a futuras generaciones. Tengo la impresión de que, a este ritmo, es difícil que nuestra generación pase a la historia como un buen ancestro. Pensándolo bien, nuestra especie evolucionó para pensar a futuro, para estudiar las estrellas, soñar con la vida después de la muerte, sembrar semillas para cosechar después. Para algunos científicos, este superpoder de "viajar mentalmente por el tiempo", es la causa de prácticamente todo lo que llamamos civilización humana. Desde la agricultura, pasando por la Carta Magna y hasta hasta Internet: todo fue concebido por la mente humana. Pero, seamos realistas, si miramos a nuestro alrededor hoy en día parece que no estamos usando este superpoder mucho que digamos. La pregunta obvia es: ¿por qué no? El error está en el diseño de nuestras comunidades, empresas e instituciones. Están diseñadas de forma tal que reducen con nuestra visión a futuro. Quiero hablarles de los tres principales errores que creo que estamos cometiendo. El primer error es lo que medimos. Los resultados trimestrales de una empresa o el valor de sus acciones a corto plazo muchas veces no son un buen indicador de que vaya a aumentar su cuota de mercado o de que vaya a ser innovadora a largo plazo. Obsesionarnos con los resultados de los exámenes escolares no es necesariamente lo mejor para la educación y la curiosidad de los niños a largo plazo. No estamos midiendo lo que es realmente importante para el futuro. El segundo error que cometemos y nos limita la visión a futuro es lo que recompensamos. Cuando celebramos a un político o a un empresario por el desastre que acaba de arreglar o el anuncio que acaba de hacer, no estamos motivando a ese líder a que invierta en prevenir esos desastres en primer lugar, o a que invierta en el futuro, ya sea protegiendo comunidades en riesgo de inundación, luchando contra la desigualdad o haciendo inversiones en investigación y educación. El tercer error que reduce nuestra visión a futuro es lo que no somos capaces de imaginar. Cuando pensamos en el futuro, en general, tratamos de predecir exactamente lo que va a suceder, ya sea con horóscopos o algoritmos. pero pasamos mucho menos tiempo imaginando todas las posibilidades del futuro. Cuando estalló la crisis del ébola en África occidental en 2014, los organismos públicos en todo el mundo contaban con señales de alerta temprana y herramientas de predicción que mostraban cómo podría llegar a propagarse el virus. Pero no se dieron cuenta de que lo haría, no intervinieron a tiempo y la epidemia avanzó hasta matar 11 000 personas. Cuando aquellos que tienen amplios recursos y buenos pronósticos no se preparan para lidiar con huracanes devastadores, es porque, muchas veces, no son capaces de imaginar lo peligrosos que pueden llegar a ser. Ahora bien, estos errores, por más deprimentes que suenen, no son inevitables. En realidad, son todos evitables. Para tomar mejores decisiones, necesitamos herramientas que nos ayuden a ver el futuro y a pensar por adelantado. Piensen en los telescopios que usaban los marineros de antaño cuando avistaban el horizonte. Solo que, en lugar de mirar a la distancia en el océano, estas herramientas miran en el tiempo hacia el futuro. Quiero hablarles de algunas herramientas que he encontrado en mis investigaciones y creo que pueden ayudarnos con nuestra visión a futuro. La primera herramienta que quiero compartir es algo así como apostar a largo plazo pero con los resultados ahora. Este es Wes Jackson, un agricultor con quien me encontré en Kansas. Jackson sabe que la mayoría de los métodos de cultivo utilizados hoy en día en todo el mundo deterioran la capa fértil de la tierra que necesitamos para alimentar a las generaciones futuras. Junto con un grupo de científicos cultivaron una variedad de grano perenne con raíces profundas que sujetan la capa fértil previniendo así la erosión y protegiendo las futuras cosechas. Pero también sabían que para incentivar a los agricultores a cultivar estos granos en el corto plazo debían aumentar el rendimiento anual y encontrar empresas dispuestas a hacer cereales y cerveza con ellos para que los agricultores pudieran ver hoy el beneficio de algo bueno para el futuro. Se ha demostrado que la estrategia funciona. De hecho, la usó George Washington Carver en el sur de los EE. UU. luego de la guerra civil a principios del siglo XX. Muchos habrán oído hablar de los 300 usos para el maní de Carver, los productos y recetas que él inventó y tanta popularidad le dieron al maní. Pero no todos saben por qué lo hizo. Estaba tratando de ayudar a los pobres agricultores en Alabama, porque sus cosechas de algodón perdían rendimiento y él sabía que, si plantaban maní, el suelo se recuperaría y el rendimiento del algodón mejoraría en los años subsiguientes. Pero también sabía que necesitaban un ingreso en el corto plazo. Hablemos ahora de otra herramienta para la visión de futuro. Esta se trata de mantener vivo el recuerdo del pasado para ayudarnos a imaginar el futuro. Fui a Fukushima, Japón, para el sexto aniversario del desastre nuclear que ocurrió luego del terremoto y del tsunami en Tohoku en 2011. Durante mi estadía me enteré de la central nuclear de Onagawa, que estaba aún más cerca del epicentro del terremoto que la infame Fukushima Daiichi, que todos conocemos. En Onagawa, la gente huyó de la ciudad para refugiarse en la central nuclear. Era así de seguro. Quedó a salvo del tsunami. Fue la previsión de un solo ingeniero, Yanosuke Hirai, que lo hizo posible. En los años 60 él abogó para que la planta se construyera más lejos de la costa, en un punto más elevado y con una escollera más alta. Conocía la historia del santuario en su ciudad natal, que se había inundado en el año 869 como consecuencia de un tsunami. Su conocimiento de la historia le permitió imaginar lo que otros no podían. OK, una herramienta más para la visión a futuro. Esta se trata de crear reliquias compartidas. Estos pescadores de langosta en la costa del Pacífico en México, son los que me enseñaron esto. Han estado protegiendo esta cosecha de langosta durante casi un siglo, y lo han conseguido porque lo ven como un recurso compartido que pasa a las manos de sus hijos y nietos. Miden cuidadosamente lo que pescan para asegurarse de agotar la langosta en el océano. En América del Norte, hay más de 30 pesquerías que están haciendo algo similar a esto. Están implementando cuotas de captura que motivan a los pescadores, no solo a capturar lo que puedan hoy, sino también a pensar en el futuro del océano. Hay muchas más herramientas para la visión a futuro que me encantaría compartir y que son muy variadas: inversionistas que ven más allá del valor de las acciones a corto plazo, países que han liberado sus elecciones de los intereses inmediatos de quienes financian la campaña. Vamos a necesitar tantas herramientas como podamos conseguir si queremos repensar lo que medimos, cambiar lo que recompensamos y ser lo suficientemente valientes como para imaginar lo que viene. Todo esto no siempre será fácil, como se imaginarán. Algunas de estas herramientas las podemos adoptar en nuestras vidas, otras las tendremos que trabajar con las empresas y las comunidades, y otras son para trabajar en sociedad. Vale la pena el esfuerzo por el futuro. My propia fuente de inspiración para esto es ese instrumento que les mostré. Se llama "dilruba", y fue hecho a medida para mi bisabuelo. Él fue un músico y crítico muy conocido en la India a principios del siglo XX. Mi bisabuelo tuvo la previsión de proteger este instrumento en una época cuando mi bisabuela estaba empeñando todas sus pertenencias, pero eso es otra historia. Lo protegió dándoselo a la próxima generación: se lo dio a mi abuela, y ella me lo dio a mí. La primera vez que escuché el sonido de este instrumento, me pareció muy evocador. Era como escuchar a un vagabundo en la niebla de los Himalayas. Era como oír una voz del pasado. (Música) (Fin de música) Ese es mi amigo Simran Singh tocando el dilruba. Cuando lo toco yo, suena como si estuvieran matando a un gato, así que de nada. (Risas) Este instrumento hoy está en mi casa, pero no me pertenece a mí. Mi rol es conducirlo a través del tiempo, y eso me parece más significativo que ser simplemente su dueña hoy. Este instrumento me posiciona como descendiente y como ancestro. Me hace sentir parte de una historia que es más grande que la mía. Y esta, a mi entender, es la forma más poderosa que tenemos de recuperar la visión a futuro: vernos como los buenos ancestros que queremos ser. ancestros no solo de nuestros hijos, sino de toda la humanidad. Sea cual fuere su reliquia, grande o pequeña, protéjanla, y sepan que su música puede resonar por generaciones. Gracias. (Aplausos)